<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An alarum of vvar given to the army and to their high court of justice (so called) revealed by the will of God in a vision to E. Poole, (sometime a messenger of the Lord to the Generall Councel, concerning the cure of the land and the manner thereof) foretelling the judgements of God ready to fall upon them for disobeying the word of the Lord in taking away the life of the king : also a letter to the congregation, in fellowship with Mr. Kissin, in vindication of E.P. ...</title>
            <author>Poole, Elizabeth.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90819</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2809</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203189</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">36281993</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 36281993</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150166</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90819)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150166)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2234:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An alarum of vvar given to the army and to their high court of justice (so called) revealed by the will of God in a vision to E. Poole, (sometime a messenger of the Lord to the Generall Councel, concerning the cure of the land and the manner thereof) foretelling the judgements of God ready to fall upon them for disobeying the word of the Lord in taking away the life of the king : also a letter to the congregation, in fellowship with Mr. Kissin, in vindication of E.P. ...</title>
                  <author>Poole, Elizabeth.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>And are to be sold in Popes-head-Ally.</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed on p. 6: Elizabeth Poole.</note>
                  <note>Caption title: A vision, wherein is manifested the disease and cure of the kingdome.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, cropped, and with print show-through, with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150166:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>An Alarum of VVar, Given to the ARMY, And to their High Court of Iuſtice (ſo called) revealed by the will of God in a Viſion to E. POOLE, (ſometime a meſſenger of the Lord to the Generall Councel, concerning the Cure of the Land, and the manner thereof.) Foretelling the judgements of God rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to fall upon them for diſobeying the word of the Lord, in taking away the life of the KING. Alſo a letter to the Congregation, in fellowſhip with Mr. <hi>Kiffin,</hi> in vindication of <hi>E. P.</hi> adviſing them to live leſſe in the Letter of the ſcripture, and more in the ſpirit.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ISAIAH</hi> 30.15, 16, 17, 18.</bibl>
               <p n="15">15. Thus ſaith the Lord God of Iſrael, In reſt and quietnes ſhall ye be ſaved: In quietneſſe and confidence ſhall be your ſtrength, and ye would not.</p>
               <p n="16">16. For ye have ſaid, No, but we will flee away upon horſes; therefore ſhall ye flee, we will ride upon the ſwifteſt, therefore ſhall your purſuers be ſwifter.</p>
               <p n="17">17. A thouſand as one ſhall flee at the rebuke of one at the rebuke of five ſhall ye flee, till ye be left as a Ship maſt on a Mountain, as a Beacon on a Hill.</p>
               <p n="18">18. Yet therefore will the Lord wait, that he may have mercy upon you, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will he be exalted, that he may have compaſſion upon you: for the Lord is the God of Judgement, bleſſed are all they that wait for him.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSAL. 68.12.</bibl>
               <p>Kings of Armies did flee apace: and ſhe that tarried at home divided the ſpoile. Wherefore ſeparate the precious from the vile, and return yee.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="vision">
            <pb facs="tcp:150166:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150166:2"/>
            <head>A Viſion, wherein is manifeſted the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe and cure of the Kingdome.</head>
            <head type="sub">Being the ſumme of what was lately delivered to the Councel of VVar; By <hi>E.P.</hi> touching the Death of the King, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIRS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have been (by the pleaſure of the moſt High) made ſenſible of the diſtreſſes of this Land, and alſo a ſympathizer with you in your labours: for having ſometimes read your <hi>Remonſtrance.</hi> I was for many dayes made a ſad mourner for her; the pangs of a travelling woman was upon me, and the pangs of death oft-times panging me, being a member in her body, of whoſe dying ſtate I was made purely ſenſible. And after many dayes mourning, a viſion was ſet before me, to ſhew her cure, and the manner of it, by this ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude: A man who is a member of the Army, having ſometimes much bewailed her ſtate, ſaying, <hi>He could gladly be a ſacrifice for her,</hi> and was ſet before me, preſenting the body of the Army; and on the other hand, a <hi>woman crooked, ſick, weak and imperfect in body,</hi> to preſent unto me, the weak and imperfect ſtate of the Kingdome: I having the gift of faith upon me for her cure, was thus to appeal to the perſon on the other hand, That he ſhould improve his faithfulneſie to the Kingdome, by uſing diligence for the cure of this woman, as I by the gift of faith on me ſhould direct him. Nevertheleſſe it is not the gift of faith in me, ſay I, nor the act of diligence in you, but in depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on the divine will, which cals me to believe, and you to act. Wherefore I being called to believe, ought not to ſtagger, neither you being called to act ſhould be ſlack: for look how farre you come ſhort of acting (as before the Lord for her cure) not according to the former rule by men preſcribed for cure, but according to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the gift of faith in me, ſo farre ſhall you come ſhort of her conſolation; and look how far you ſhall act as before the Lord, with diligence for her cure, you ſhall be made partakers of her conſolation.</p>
            <p>I am therefore to ſigniſie unto you, that there is but one ſtep be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween you and reſtauration, the which whoſoever taketh not wari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhall ſtumble, and fall, and be taken, and that is this; you are to ſtand as in the preſence of the Lord, to be dead unto all your own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, lives liberties, freedoms, or whatſoever you might call yours: yet pleading for them ſtill with men, ſpeaking to every one in his own
<pb facs="tcp:150166:3"/>language, for they are your due with them; but except you are as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to reſigne them up to the will of the eternall pleaſure, as to plead them with men, you ſhall ſurely loſe them; <hi>For he that will ſave his life ſhall loſe it, and he that will loſe it ſhall ſave it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord hath a controverſie with the great and mighty men of the earth, with the Captains, and Rulers, and Governours: You may be great and mighty upon the earth, and maintaine his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, but againſt the mighty men of the earth is his controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie held: For as you are the potſherd of the earth, he will ſurely break you to pieces, till there bee not a ſherd left to carry coales on. The Kingly power is undoubtedly fallen into your hands; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my advice is, that you take heed to improve it for the Lord. You have juſtly blamed thoſe who have gone before you, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying their truſt therein. I ſpeak not this as you are ſouldiers, but as the ſpirit of Judgement and Juſtice is moſt lively appearing in you, this is therefore the great work which lyeth upon you, to become dead to every pleaſant picture, which might preſent it ſelf for your delight, that you perfectly dying in the will of the Lord, you may finde your reſurrection in him.</p>
            <p>She being after demanded, <hi>Whether ſhe had any direction to give the Councel?</hi> She anſwered, no: for the preſent, for ſhe was in this caſe preſented to her ſelf as the Church, which ſpirit is in you, an ſhall guide you.</p>
            <p>She being afterwards asked by ſome of the chief Officers, <hi>Whether ſhe conceived they were called to deliver up the truſt to them committed either to Parliament or People?</hi> She anſwered, No, for this reaſon, it being committed to their care and truſt, it ſhould certainly be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at their hands, but take them with you as younger brethren, who may be helpfull to you: Nevertheleſſe know you are in the place of watchmen, wherefore ſlack not your watch over them, for <hi>the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Stewardſhip ſhall be required at your hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was further ſaid unto her, <hi>How then ſhall we be free from the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſions of the people, who will be ready to judge that we improve this intereſt for our own ends?</hi> She anſwered, Set your ſelves, as before the Lord, to diſcharge the truſt committed to you, and truſt him with your reward: I ſpeak not this that you ſhould be exalted above your brethren, but that you might ſtand in faithfulneſſe to diſcharge your duty; <hi>For he that will ſave his life ſhall loſe it, and he that will loſe it, ſhall ſave it.</hi> You have been Noble-men, behaving your ſelves with much valour and courage (as amongſt men) now therefore loſe
<pb facs="tcp:150166:3"/>not your reward, for this will be the greateſt piece of courage that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you were made the examples of; if you ſhall be as well content to loſe houſe, land, wife and children, or what ever you might call yours in divine will, as ever you were to lay down your lives in the field.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>SIRS,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Have conſidered the agreement of the people that is before you, and I am very jealous leſt you ſhould betray your truſt in it (in as much as the Kingly Power is faln into your hands) in giving it up to the people; for thereby you give up the truſt committed to you, and in ſo doing you will prove your ſelves more treacherous then they that went before you, they being no wayes able to improve it without you. You juſtly blame the King for betraying his truſt, and the Parliament for betraying theirs: This is the great thing I have to ſay to you, Betray not you your truſt.</p>
            <p>I have yet another Meſſage to ſhew you, I know not what accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance it may finde with you, yet I am content, here it is, let it finde what acceptance it may, I leave it with you.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="message">
            <head>The Meſſage is as followeth:</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Sirs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving already found ſo free admiſſion into your preſences, it hath given me the greater incouragement (though more pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly, the truth perſwading me thereunto) to preſent you with my thoughts in theſe following lines. I am in divine pleaſure made ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of the might of the affaires which lye upon you; and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of ſympathie abiding in me, conſtraineth me to groan with you in your pains; you may remember I told you, the Kingly power is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly fallen into your hands, which power, is to puniſh evil doers, and to praiſe them that doe well: Now therefore my cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble advice to you is, that you ſtand as in the awfull preſence of the moſt high Father, acting your parts before God and man, you ſtand in the place of interpreters, for many hard ſayings preſent themſelves to you, and will do, look for it: wherefore ſee,</p>
            <p>That you give unto men the things that are theirs, and unto God the things that are his, it is true indeed, as unto men (I know I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale by the gift of God upon me) the King is your Father and hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, which you were and are to obey in the Lord, and no other way, for when he forgot his Subordination to divine Father-hood &amp; head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, thinking he had begotten you a generation to his own pleaſure, and taking you a wife for his own luſts, thereby is the yoak taken from your necks (I mean the neck of the Spirit and Law, which is the
<pb facs="tcp:150166:4"/>bond of your union, that the holy life in it might not be prophaned, it being free and can not be bound. <hi>For the law of the Spirit of life in Chriſt Jeſus, hath freed us from the law of ſin and of death,</hi> for the letter of the law, which ſpeaketh to the fleſh killeth, therefore you muſt ſuffer of men in the fleſh, for the Lords ſake, that ſo dying to your own bodies (that is to all ſelf intereſt in divine will) your might alſo receive your reſurrection, for you muſt dye before you can riſe, you muſt looſe your lives, Intereſts, Liberties, and all (before you can ſave them) caſting your Crowne at the feet of the Lamb, who only is worthy; yet ſtill pleading for them with men, for they are your due with them, a ſhare they may not deny you; <hi>Bleſſed are the dead which die in the Lord: for they reſt from their labours, and their works doe follow them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From your own labours, I wiſh you reſt in the Lord, that the fruit of your labours, which is the life of your faith may follow you to priſon, and to death; know this, that true liberty either is not bound to any thing, nor from any thing, for it is ſubject to this or that (neither this nor that in divine will) nevertheleſſe as from the Lord you have all that you have, and are ſo to the Lord, you owe all that you have, and are for his own name ſake. So from the King in Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination.</p>
            <p>You have all that you have and are, and alſo in Subordination you owe him all that you have and are, and although hee would not bee your father and husband, Subordinate, but abſolute, yet know that you are for the Lords ſake to honour his perſon. For he is the Father and Husband of your bodyes, as unto men, and therefore your right cannot bee without him, as unto men, I know and am very ſenſible, that no ſmall ſtraight lyeth upon you in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of ſecuring his perſon (for the manifold conceived in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences following, and neceſſities of evill event) in reſpect of raiſing more wars, and alſo other things well known to you, which will preſent themſelves unpoſſible for you to avoid, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, this is my humble and hearty prayer to the everlaſting Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (which I preſent to you in words, that you may bee edified thereby) Remember I ſaid, everlaſting Father, for ſo we ſhall beſt know him for our conſolation; that it might pleaſe him of his infinite, eternall life and goodneſſe to grant you a ſure and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine knowledge of this, that all things which are impoſſible with men (at the utmoſt extent of impoſſibillity) are poſſible with him, who only ſaith it, and it commeth to paſſe, the Lord of hoaſts,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:150166:4"/>the God of the whole earth, who commandeth all hoaſts of men, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Devils, whoſe eyes run to and fro throughout the face of the whole earth: To ſhew himſelfe ſtrong in the behalf of all thoſe that truſt in him: wherefore put your ſwords into his hands for your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and fear not to act the part of <hi>Abigail,</hi> ſeing <hi>Nabal</hi> hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed it (by Appropriating his goods to himſelf) in relieving <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> and his men in their diſtreſle; it was to her praiſe, it ſhall be to yours fear it not: Onely conſider, that as ſhe lifted not her hand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her husband to take his life, no more doe ye againſt yours.</p>
            <p>For as the Lord revenged his own cauſe on him, he ſhall do on yours; <hi>For vengeance is mine, I will repay it, ſaith the Lord;</hi> who made him the Saviour of your body, though hee hath profaned his Saviour-ſhip; Stretch not forth the hand againſt him: For know this, the Conqueſt was not without divine pleaſure, whereby Kings came to reigne, though through luſt they tyrannized: which God excuſeth not, but judgeth; and his judgements are fallen heavy, as you ſee, upon <hi>Charles</hi> your Lord: Forget not your pitty towards him, for you were given him an helper in the body of the people: Which people are they that agreed with him to ſubject unto the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of evill doers, and the praiſe of them that doe well: which law is the ſpirit of your Union: And although this bond be broken on his part; You never heard that a wife might put away her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, as he is the head of her body; but for the Lords ſake ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his terrour to her fleſh, though ſhe be free in the ſpirit to the Lord; and he being uncapable to act as her husband, ſhe acteth in his ſtead; and having the ſpirit of Union abiding in her, ſhee conſidereth him in his temptations, as tempted with him: And if he will uſurpe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver her, ſhe appealeth to the Fatherhood for her offence, which is the ſpirit of Juſtice, and is in you; For I know no power in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to whom it is committed, ſave your ſelves (and the preſent Parliament) which are to act in the Church of Chriſt, as ſhee by the gift of faith upon her, ſhall be your guide for the cure of her body, that you might therefore commit an unſound member to Sathan (though the head) as it is fleſh; that the ſpirit might be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the day of the Lord (I believe) And accordingly you may hold the hands of your husband, that he pierce not your bowels with a knife or ſword to take your life. Neither may you take
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150166:5"/>his, I ſpeak unto you as Men, Fathers, and Brethren in the Lord. (who are to walk by this rule) Whatſoever you would that men ſhould doe unto you, doe yee the ſame unto them: I know it would affright you to be cut off in your iniquity; but O, how fain would you have your iniquity taken away! Conſider alſo others in their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement; I know you have ſaid it, and I believe, that if you could ſee ſuitable ſorrow for ſo great offence, you ſhould embrace it: I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you in the bowels of love, for there it is I pleade with you, look upon the patience of God towards you, and ſee if it will not conſtrain you to forbearance for his ſake: I know the ſpirit of ſanctity is in you; and I know as well the ſpirit of bondage holdeth you oft-times, that you cannot but groane for deliverance: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I beſeech you for the Lords ſake, whoſe I am, and whom I ſerve in the ſpirit, that you let not goe the Viſion which I ſhewed you concerning the cure of <hi>England,</hi> as it was preſented to mee: Wherein the party acting, being firſt required to ſtand, as in the awfull preſence of God, and to act for her cure, according to the direction which he ſhould receive from the Church, by the gift of faith upon her: (Act he muſt) but not after any former rule by men preſcribed for cure, (but after the rule of the gift of faith) which I humbly beſeech the Almighty Lord to eſtabliſh in you. I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your ſervant in the Church and Kingdome of Chriſt. Elizabeth Poole.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>After the delivery of this, ſhe was asked, whether ſhe ſpake againſt the bringing of him to tryall, or againſt their taking of his life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>She anſwered, Bring him to his tryall, that he may be convicted in his conſcience, but touch not his Perſon.</hi>
               </p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:150166:5"/>
            <head>A Friend to truth and of the Authors to the Reader.</head>
            <p>THe occaſion of the next enſuing Letter (written by <hi>T. P.</hi> in vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of the Author) was this, the Author Mrs. <hi>E. Poole</hi> having delivered a Meſſage of the Lord to the Generall Counſell of the Army forewarning them againſt that great ſin, fore told of by the Apoſtle to be the ſin of theſe latter dayes, <hi>viz.</hi> Selfe-love, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking of which, would be a great ſtop and let to the Independent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, <hi>viz.</hi> the taking away the life of the King: there aroſe diverſe falſe witneſſes, <hi>viz. W. K.</hi> Mr. <hi>P.</hi> and Mr. <hi>John Fountaine,</hi> but none of theſe ſtood to the publike teſt but Mr. <hi>Fountaine,</hi> who endeavouring to weaken the Meſſage by ſcandalizing and reproaching the Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, charging her with ſome follies committed many yeares agoe, and long ſince repented of, and with other things ſhe knew not: The old Serpentine trick new revived, but in a finer dreſs: For it is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to thee (good Reader) how the Lord Chriſt, when in fleſh, was called a glutton, a wine bibber, a friend of Publicans and Harlots, and ſhall Chriſt in ſpirit, thinke you, fare any better? As alſo thou art not ignorant of that place in <hi>Math. 13 25.</hi> where it ſaith the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven is likened unto a man which ſowed good ſeed in his feild, but while men ſlept his Enemy came and ſowed tares among the wheat and went his way: this man is the Lord from Heaven, who ſends his Servant to ſow right good ſeed <hi>viz.</hi> wheat, the word of God, the Child Jeſus, in his feild even your hearts, but while you ſleepe the Enemy comes, (the Devill, the accuſer of the brethren, who alwayes comes in a ſleeping time, in the night, and dark underſtandings of men, when they are commanded from him to watch) and ſtealingly ſoweth tares among the wheat, on purpoſe to choake the wheat, or at leaſt to cauſe it to be deſpiſed, upon the inſtant of time when Chriſt was borne in the fleſh, King <hi>Herod</hi> fearing his Kingdome and government ſhould be taken from him, ſent forth <note n="*" place="margin"> Mat. 2.16.</note> and ſlew all the children that were in <hi>Bethlehem</hi> and in all the Coaſts thereof, this was a figure of that which was to come, to be done upon the firſt appearings of Chriſt in ſpirit, for as the child of the bond-woman did perſecute the childe of the free-woman, ſo they that are borne after the fleſh, doe perſecute them that are borne after the ſpirit, and the firſt borne of the forme will perſecute them that come in the power of the moſt high, you know the Story in the <hi>12.</hi> of the <hi>Revelations</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin"> Rev. 12.1, 2.3, 4, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 6. &amp;c.</note> of the woman cloathed with the Suane <hi>&amp;c.</hi> being with child cried traveling in birth, and pained <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> deliuered; and a great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>gon having <hi>7.</hi> heads <hi>&amp;c</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:150166:6"/>before the woman, &amp;c. to devoure her childe as ſoon as it was born; the iſſue of it was, the great Dragon was caſt out, the old Serpent cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Devil and Satan the accuſer of the Brethren: and I make no queſtion, but the ſame effect it ſhall have upon ſome; I pray let theſe things be conſidered by thee, <note place="margin">ver. 9.10.</note> the Lord himſelf will make application of this in due time to the hearts of theſe refined perſecutors,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>The Copy of a letter, as it was ſent from <hi>T. P.</hi> a friend of Mrs. <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth Poole,</hi> To the Congregation of Saints, walking in fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with Mr. <hi>William Kiffin.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>DEar brethren in the bowels of love and meeknes, I kindely ſalute you, wiſhing you an encreaſe of all faithfulnes and true knowledg in the myſtery of Chriſt: The cauſe of my preſent writing is to acquaint you, that providence hath lately brought a letter to my hand, directed to my husband, concerning one Mrs. <hi>Poole,</hi> once a member with you; which woman ſay you, for ſcandalous evils was caſt out: Now it being ſome years ſince it was done, I humbly deſire a little to reaſon with you about the grounds, why this ſtill remains upon your ſpirits, ſeeing Chriſt ſaith, <hi>forgive yee one another, as I forgive you;</hi> and God is ſaid to remember our ſins no more; this therefore is a note of forgiveneſſe not to remember, and ſure we ſhould ſhew our ſelves children of our heavenly father; but further I deſire before the Lord, that you examine your own hearts in this thing, what your end is in it; if it be, you think, ſhe is not worthy to have a livelihood amongſt men, then why doe you not either by the Civill Law, if that will take hold of the offence, or by ſome other way, if nothing will ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie you but her blood, take ſome preſent courſe that may put an end to this great difference: but if you think this be too groſſe, or more then the offence requires; then I beſeech you, for the Lords ſake, to conſider your own actings in this thing, whether you do not as much as in you lyes, carry on the ſame deſigne, though more cloſly from the eyes of the world, but ſure before the Lord it can appear no other, but the hunting after her life; nay is it not more then to take off one ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle life at once? or which is greater cruelty, for a Tyrant to take a man life at once? or by degrees; and then your ſelves be judges, whether your proceedings towards her be not a killing all the day long: for you cannot be ignorant that ſhe hath no livelihood amongſt men, but what ſhe earns by her hands: and your defaming her in this manner
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:150166:6"/>cannot in an ordinary way but deprive her of that, and ſo at laſt bring her blood upon you: if you ſay, you acquaint none but the Saints with it, that is evident to the contrary, for your open publiſhing it in the Councell of War, cauſed the world to take notice of it, and yet your ſpirits reſt not here; truly dear friends, as the evil ſpirit wrought in her one way, when with you; ſo conſider whether the ſame ſpirit, do not highly work in you at this time another way; the Lord give you underſtanding in all things: But if her life be not that which you aim at, then is it theſe divine diſcoveries of life and light, which God makes out to the world by her: if it be ſo, then you are to know, that he is too ſtronge you ſtrive with; but about this I would a little quere: firſt, whether do you think that becauſe ſuch evils were mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in her, when with you; therefore it is impoſſible now that any good ſhould be brought forth by her: do you not hope to grow bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and better. But ſecondly, is it not Gods uſuall way to manifeſt himſelf there higheſt, where in time paſt he was by the evil ſpirit kept loweſt; yea, doth he not ſuffer himſelf for this very end many times, thus to die in appearance, and to leave a ſoule to it ſelf, that ſo it may ſee what it is in it ſelf, and ſo learn to die to it ſelf, that ſo he may have the more glorious reſurrection in that ſoul. I beſeech you for the Lord ſake to conſider theſe things: as for her outward perſon, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſhe cares as little for it as you can, therefore you may take your fill of trampling on it; but I beſeech you be carefull how you medle with the ſpirit that breaths in her, for ſurely brethren, I know not what ſpirit manifeſted it ſelf in her while with you; I am ſure, and I ſpeak nothing but the truth, that I have found a moſt divine ſpirit in her, as far as I could diſcern, and that which comes to the ſpirit and life of things, and in this methinks you ſhould rejoyce, for truly, I have heard many profeſſors and profeſſions, but to my knowledge I never heard one come ſo near the power, I do not ſpeak this as being affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with any perſon, party, or opinion; I bleſſe my God, I am now in his ſtrength; delivered from that, though ſome have falſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed my being deluded by her, but I am confident I can ſay with <hi>Paul,</hi> and that not onely repeating the letter, but in truth; that thoſe things which I have received, have not been from man, nor woman, nor any other thing, but by the meer revelation of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in me, God manifeſting himſelf in my own fleſh; and therefore they much wrong both her, and me, that affirm it, but eſpecially they wrong or ſpeak a lye of that God that did it for me: and becauſe I hear it ſo reported amongſt you, I thought good to write one word
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150166:7"/>to clear it, that ſo whether you will hear, or whether you will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear the word of truth might judge you; give not ear therefore to all you heare though from brethren, leaſt you be brought into a ſnare; for ſince the defection of the Churches men, yea good men have been ſuch lovers of themſelves and their own opinions, that they will ſpeak largely, upon little ground, to keep up their own glory; God having not yet undone them, for were they once undone men, they would willingly be what God would have them, however the world ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts of them; there is another thing which came to my ear, that it ſhould be given into the Councel by your two witneſſes, that the ſaid Mrs. <hi>Poole</hi> ſhould ſay, that you caſt her out for difference in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and when Coll. <hi>Reeth</hi> and Coll. <hi>Hariſon</hi> asked to whom ſhe ſpake it, they ſaid to ſome of <hi>Abington:</hi> now indeed my husband ſaid to you, that he thought ſuch a thing, but when he came home and ſee ſo little ground for his thoughts, I think he had but little comfort in telling you ſo; and then brethren if you upon ſuch ſlender grounds ſhould act in this ſtrange manner againſt her, affirming this thing ſo publikely, I think you have cauſe to be humbled for it, and juſtly to repent of your evil; I deſire you to bear a little with me, for truly it appears to me, rather to be your rage of ſpirit, then your true love, either to her, or truth, for me thinks it would ſavour more of a true Chriſtian ſpirit if you had firſt ſpoken with her, and have ſeen what change the Lord hath wrought in her, as knowing that <hi>Mary</hi> out of whom ſeven Devils had been formerly caſt, <hi>was made</hi> the firſt meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Chriſt Reſurrection; yea, and ſhe muſt bring it to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and not the Apoſtles to her: You ſay in your letter that you left her to the judgement of the great day, and I beſeech you brethren, do you not again take her into your own daie, for truly I believe that daie in a meaſure hath come upon her, and the Lord himſelf is at work with her, therefore do not feare but the work will bee well done, onely we as well as ſhe muſt have patience in it, and ſurely this is the confidence that I have concerning her, that ſhe hath ſeen evill in that eſtate ſhe walked in with you, and certainlie God is good to her in this, ſhewing her what an abominable ſpirit of wickedneſſe may be hid under the greateſt practices and profeſſions of externals, not that theſe are the cauſe of it; no, the gold and the ſilver is mine, ſaith the Lord; but we beſtowing it upon our lovers, and making our ſelves great with his ornaments, he is fain, in love to us, to take us from them, or they from us, and ſo finde out a more ſpeciall adminiſtration to perfect us in: Oh the infinite riches of our God! where doth his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150166:7"/>bountie end, ſure his waies of love are unſearchable, and his paths of mercy, in which he follows poore fallen man, and poore backſliding ſouls, are past finding out, how narrow are our capacities, we judge as men, we may think as ſome did of <hi>David,</hi> that there is no help for ſuch things in God, but all things in truth will be found poſſible with him, even where they are altogether paſt our thoughts and concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and become to us impoſſible; I beſeech you therefore be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to bow down to him; I know you are conſcious, that all judgement is not committed unto you, and therefore it is poſſible you may not judge right in this thing; for truly brethren we may conceive many things even by the letter it ſelf, and yet not living in that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that writ the Letter, we may erre, I pray do not miſtake me as if I would any way ſpeak ſlightly of the letter, farther than it ſpeaks of it ſelf; no, I bleſſe the Father for it, and by ſweet experience can ſay, that I was never ſo confirmed in it, now the Lord hath drawn me to him out of it, even in that ſpirit that wrought it; I am for the conſcionable uſe of it, but I would not abuſe it; I am ſure, thoſe men that would ſet it above the ſpirit, can hardly free themſelves from that thing, I hope therefore you will not count it your excellency to walk in the letter, but rather deſire the Lord to perfect you in that ſpirit that writes the letter for then and never but then ſhall we be able to walk by right, and ſpeak of the letter truly: I have not yet acquainted my husband with your letter. I ſhall wait upon God what anſwer to receive from you: for truly dear brethren, upon ſerious deliberation, I know not how to approve my ſelfe faithfull in the eies of God to my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren here, if I ſhould deliver it; for God having put it into my hand, I muſt alſo ſee clearnes from him before I part with it: for though bleſſed be the father, we have a ſweet hopefull people amongſt us that wait upon God, and have fellowſhip one with another; yet whether they may digeſt ſuch things as you write of, I really queſtion; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it would be unfaithfulnes in me, if I apprehending an evil to them, or any other, ſhould not as much as in me lies prevent it; and this I ſhall do, by detaining the Letter, till further manifeſtation from God what to do with it do not judge me in this thing, I beſeech you: I have one Judge, even the Lord, and he that put it into my hand, will at length clear my integrity in it, I have nothing to doe for my ſelf in it, the Lord knows; onely,</p>
            <p>How I may approve my ſelfe faithfull to men in the Lord and for the Lords ſake; your deſire I exceedingly like, that we may be kept from errors, and the Lord keepe us from all errors, but who muſt ſhew us what errour is, but the God of truth himſelfe, wee
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150166:8"/>have lived in error, and have ſuckt them in from our cradles, and yet who will ſpeake ſo much againſt error as wee, ſtating our ſelves ſtill in the truth, my ſweet friends, the day of truth is but now dawning upon us, and how is it oppoſed, yea by thoſe that are children of truth, in their meaſure; yet wee have all looked for it, and prayed together for it a long time, but truly now wee will not own our prayers, but turne away our face from our Saviour, becauſe hee comes not in ſuch a garb as we imagined he would, when we know its his prerogative to cloath himſelfe with what fleſh, orgarment he pleaſes, brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren what would you have, doe you not know that a glorious day hath beene ſpoken of ever ſince the Prophets, and the Apoſtles: Though the day was dawned upon them, yet they bid their hearts not to be terrified, as if that day were neare, for ſaith he there muſt be a falling away firſt, and that wicked one be revealed, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Peter</hi> tould them that he was a partaker of that glory, that ſhould bee afterwards revealed, however ſaith he, you have a ſure word of Propheſie to which yee doe well to take heed, as if he had ſaid, brethren, wee have beene with the Lord in the mount, and have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held that excellent glory, but yet to you that have not ſo ſeene Chriſt there is a more ſure word of Propheſie; for viſions and revelations doe moſt eſpecially confirme and ſtrengthen thoſe that have them, but here is a word that is ſpoken to all, and is as a light ſhining in a darke place, therefore you doe well to take heed to it till the day dawne, and the day Star ariſe in your owne hearts, and you be ſwallowed up with that glory, that now you expect and wait for, onely know this, that no private ſpirit can underſtand theſe Scriptures that ſpeake of that day, it muſt be the ſpirit of God alone, let us ceaſe from our own Spirits therefore, for they are ſelfiſh and private, bound up to this and that, and ſo it would confine God alſo, but his Spirit is as large as himſelfe, its without bonds, its neither here nor there diſtinct, but it is individually every where. But that which I deſire you to conſider from theſe Scriptures is, that this day of falling away hath beene; and all the world hath wandred after the beaſt, ſince the Apoſtles time; therefore how neare may we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect our glory: wee ſhould not be troubling our ſelves therefore ſtill with falling a way, but now looke for a riſing, for ſure man hath his day, and now the Lord will have his day: now ſeeing this day of the Lord muſt have a dawning, and ſome Diſciples may bee taken up into the Mount, before other ſome, it ſhould teach us not to judge our brethren, that ſpeake of higher injoyments then we have, for wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150166:8"/>behind ſhould rather judge our ſelves, ſeeing we are more in the day of man, and acknowledge our ſelves ſo to bee, ſtill looking for, and haſtening to the day of God, in which wee may act ſelfe nor ſelfiſhly, no longer, but our God may bring forth his owne righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe in us: and truly brethren you may bee ſatisfied in this, that wee are verily induſtrious to keepe our ſelves from error, but wee know that in his ſtrength wee ſhall bee perfected, and when himſelfe comes and ſpeakes, then ſhall we know that it is hee; and truly bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren, I would not have you infidels but believing, this day hath taken ſome unawares, and though many may have it in notion yet I am ſure that ſome have it in power, I have one thing more to you concerning your Letter, and truly I cannot but wonder at it, that is, how you durſt ſo peremptorily to judge the woman that ſhee brought a delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for a viſion of God, I beſeech you conſider ſeriouſly before the Lord, whether you are ſure that it was ſo or no, before you make it ſo publike, and ſend it forth with the authority of a Church, ſurely friends, you will much abuſe the authority of your Church, in affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming mere ſuppoſition for truth, the Lord be pleaſed to open your eys in this thing, it may be your father in mercy deſires, a little to plead with you by a weake Inſtrument, and therefore put the letter into my hand, that ſo he might put ſome ſtop to your furious driving, &amp; truly I can looke upon it no other wayes; therefore willingly meet your God in this mercifull act towards you, for if you doe not, the dumb Aſſe next time may reprove you, I confeſſe, ſoules, I am the weakeſt of all, a poore undone ſoule in my ſelfe, the Lord alone take all the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, yet if I may bee uſefull, as being one of the body, in keeping you from doing greater evils, I ſhall be willing and rejoyce, though I goe under never ſo great an odium my ſelfe, for ſure freinds, account of me how you will, I am one of you, and tenderly affect you, and in this thing would have God truly exalted: For this grace is given me to love truth under any appearance, though indeed, that may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times appeare to men to bee truth which I cannot cloſe with; but I mean any appearance that my God comes in, and I hope ſhal be more and more perfected in it; and indeed it is ſweet to mee that he hath given me, through mercy, to know his voyce from a ſtranger, it may be the world may judge me for it, becauſe it comes not in their form, but I ſhal reſt in the Lord: wel brethren, if you ſee mercy to you in that which the Lord hath ſpoken by me, receive it and rejoyce in him, it may be I may prove to you as <hi>Abigail</hi> did to <hi>David,</hi> keep you from ſhedding blood, &amp; from avenging your ſelves with your owne
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:150166:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>hand, the Lord ſhew us therefore what that ſcripture meaneth, <hi>I will have mercy and not ſacrifices:</hi> there be many things in the letter of the ſcripture, which we through weaknes may think to be ſacrifices, as the Phariſees did, when God abhors it, and will have none of it, in ſuch a time as he cals for mercy; therefore hee bids us learn what that meaneth: we may have it, and read it, and ſpeak it, but to learn the inſide of it, learn what it meaneth, will be our comfort, and our Crown; and truly my dear friends, I am perſwaded, that this is a time, in which, mercy is required of us towards our Siſter, and not ſuch ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices: If you pleaſe to ſend me a word of an anſwer, leave it with M. <hi>Calvert,</hi> at the Black ſpred Eagle at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls;</hi> I do not think it fit as yet, that you acquaint my husband with it, not for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfulneſſe ſake, but conveniency; for ſurely brethren, I am not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly carryed, to give you or him, or any one offence, onely as the Lord manifeſts it to be his will, and then I muſt leave Father, and mother, and all, and cleave to him. Let me have your anſwer as ſoon as you can: but I beſeech you, do not anſwer me, but the Lord, and then ſee how you can juſtifie your ſelves; in him therefore ſhall I wait for it, and dear ſouls, though I am nothing, and can doe nothing in my ſelf; yet I beſeech you do not reject any word of truth, love, and ſincerity that God ſends by my hand. <hi>Job</hi> ſaith He did not reject the cauſe of his Maid ſervant when it came before him, though the word ſaid, they contended with him: I can give you more ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on if you pleaſe how I came by the letter, I am ſure it was unexpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by me, onely the Lord would have it ſo; and therefore all your care muſt ſerve the Lords deſignes, to bring it to my hand when my husband was not in town: do not therefore look upon me, but look to the Lord, and uſe me as kindely as <hi>Job</hi> did his ſervant, reject not my cauſe, for ſurely it is not mine; I leave you to the Lord, in whom I deſire rightly to guide you in this thing, and am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your ſincere loving Siſter and ſervant, from the greateſt to the meaneſt of you, <hi>T. P.</hi>
               </signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Abington:</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6. <hi>March</hi> 1649.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata in Alarum.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 4. <hi>line</hi> 1. <hi>for</hi> have done, <hi>read</hi> have done to be righteous. <hi>pag.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>li.</hi> 27. <hi>for</hi> and your, <hi>r.</hi> but you your: <hi>p.</hi> 7. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>for</hi> are <hi>r. were</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>l.</hi> 14. <hi>for</hi> as appeareth for, <hi>r.</hi> as appeareth in that: <hi>l.</hi> 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>r.</hi> call the: <hi>l.</hi> 22. <hi>for</hi> call the, <hi>r.</hi> call it the: <hi>p.</hi> 9 <hi>l.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> taken viz. <hi>l.</hi> 24. <hi>for</hi> ſay, <hi>r.</hi> ſaid: <hi>p.</hi> 11. <hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>for</hi> e are, <hi>r.</hi> yee are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>l.</hi> 15. <hi>for</hi> the ſea, <hi>r.</hi> theſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150166:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
